What did the French army look like in
the Hundred Years' War?
And following its devastation at the
hands of a grueling conflict and the
Black Death, how was it resurrected by a
young girl of just 17?
Starting from but a handful of
companions on a foolhardy mission to
save [music] the realm
to a small company delivering supplies
to a besieged Orléans
to the hundreds who rallied to her
banner to save the city
the thousands who helped reclaim the
Loire and eventually the tens of
thousands accompanying her holy mission
to the gates of Paris.
It's a story so incredible, it's hard to
believe.
Joan of Arc was truly a unique figure in
the Middle Ages.
A peasant girl with no military
background or training who rose from
nothing to turn the tide of one of the
most important medieval wars.
She led from the front, being shot down
and maimed on multiple occasions, but
each time returning to the fore more
zealous than before.
Motivated by divine inspiration and
French proto-nationalism,
she reinvigorated a French army that had
been slowly losing ground in the war for
the French crown and seemed on the edge
of defeat.
In this video, we will consider the
military that she inspired in the
context of the changes that were
occurring [music] in late medieval
armies at this time, such as
new recruitment methods
technological advancements
military strategy and more.
We bring it all together with a coverage
of her campaigns.
From the siege of Orléans
to the pivotal Battle of Patay
and the siege of Paris.
This is the true size of the holy army
of Joan of Arc.
>> This video was actually produced with
our friends over at History Adventures.
They're a new channel which brings to
life the past with immersive
storytelling and high production value.
I love that Alina actually shows viewers
the historical sites of her stories and
makes use of creative artistry like sand
painting to provide unique and appealing
visuals.
Her sets are incredible and as a fellow
YouTuber I'm incredibly jealous of not
just the way she presents the
information, but just the overall
character of her channel.
Her videos are not just informative and
approachable, but include a lot of
nuance when it comes to questioning
primary sources and providing viewpoints
from different academics. For our own
video today, I definitely recommend you
check out the full video on Joan of Arc
from Alina as it provides a lot more of
the background political and personal
information for the story.
Also, be sure to check out Alina's other
recent videos on topics like ancient
Cambodia and the Phoenicians. I can't
recommend her channel enough, so check
it out.
>> Unfortunately, the sources for Joan of
Arc's army are surprisingly limited.
So much ink was spilled about Joan's
[music] beliefs, her meteoric rise, her
role as an inspirational leader,
>> [music]
>> and the injustice of her trial and
execution after she was captured by the
English.
But, that left little remaining for the
details of the army she was given even
in our main sources like the French
journal of the siege of Orléans
or the chronicle of the maid.
This means we have to make educated
guesses from less precise sources
[music]
about the organization of late medieval
French armies in general and what is
described in the sources [music] about
Joan of Arc's campaigns specifically and
try to bring them together.
But, even that has a major problem which
we will explore later.
First, we should briefly recap the
nature [music] of the French army and
the Hundred Years War.
Going into the Hundred Years War, the
French army of the early 14th [music]
century was still based on the old
banner system, which had long been a
fixture of the medieval era.
To sum it up briefly, an army would be
raised by the ruler calling in their
vassals, each of whom would either bring
soldiers or provide money in place of
soldiers.
This would continue down the vassal
chain as each individual in the
hierarchy called upon their own
followers to do the same.
In battle, such vassals were grouped
together under literal [music] banners
with increasingly large banners being
assembled in an ad hoc manner.
The French version of this was informed
by the particular nature of their realm.
Here, the lands of the Capetian kings
were broken up into various regions with
the king directly ruling the royal
domain centered around Paris.
The crown would call out [music] the ban
and raise an army known as the host.
This summons applied to the personal
vassals of the king, as well as the
towns of each prevote or military
region,
whose charter specified a particular
military obligation of local militia.
In theory, all lords of France were
expected to answer the call to arms, but
in practice, their participation was a
reflection of the relative strength of
the monarchy, which waxed and waned over
the years.
Technically, the calling out of the ban
was also supposed [music] to extend all
the way down to all free land holding
men.
However, the obligations of such common
folk was usually not required outside of
emergencies,
>> [music]
>> when the peasantry could be mobilized as
part of the arriere-ban
or general levy.
Lastly, the army would be reinforced by
mercenary troops, many of whom came from
beyond the kingdom, such as lands of
Western Germany or the Italian
city-states.
At the ground level, answering the call
to arms [music] would have been troops
equipped in the manner of their age.
For the 1300s, this meant that [music]
the most high-end warriors were noble
knights who came with a horse, a lance,
a shield, mail armor with some plate
reinforcement, and [music] an iron or
steel helmet, as well as additional
support personnel.
It was a tremendously expensive kit,
with nobility being ranked largely based
on their ability to provide men and
gear.
Alongside them [music] came the
non-noble sergeants, who were less
well-equipped and supported, but
nonetheless represented sturdy troops,
which might fight on horse or on foot.
Next came the militiamen, who donned
simpler armor, such as the quilted
gambeson, [music]
and either melee or ranged weapons.
Of growing prominence were the
crossbowmen, whose piercing bolts were
key to countering increasingly armored
troops.
And lastly, were the mercenaries, who
might come as any manner of mounted,
melee, or ranged troop type.
We should also mention that very early
gunpowder units had begun to be deployed
in the form of the organ gun and the
poudre de fer.
Though they made an impression, they
were very rare and were often as much a
danger to their users as to the enemy.
When in the field, these soldiers could
be organized in many forms. Here,
individual banners might scale from
around 5 to 50 men, depending on the
troop type.
All of whom would be commanded by a
single officer.
Minor lords would command a group of
such banners numbering in hundreds.
These often featured a mix of units
reflective of the nature of their
vassals.
Major lords, meanwhile, could be
expected to call up thousands of men,
which likely included a healthy number
of mounted and [music] foot troops.
When all such banners were called to
meet the king, their numbers could truly
swell.
Here, we have presented an indicative
host that was historically deployed in
the early 14th century.
Its banners hailed from counties and
duchies across the realm, with
additional support called from beyond.
In this incarnation, the assembled army
of France brought with them some 8,000
mounted men-at-arms, 5,000 crossbowmen,
5,000 assorted infantry, and thousands
more support forces for a total of
nearly 20,000 fighting men.
It is a strong medieval host in an era
when centralization had not yet allowed
for a return to the truly massive armies
of antiquity.
This was the army which the French
brought to bear at the start of the
Hundred Years' War.
Let us now briefly trace [music] its
unfolding to set the stage for the rise
of Joan of Arc.
The Hundred Years' War was precipitated
in 1328 when King Charles IV of France
died without sons or brothers to succeed
him.
French nobles chose his cousin, Count
Philip of Valois, as his heir, but his
nephew, King Edward the III of England,
claimed the throne through his mother,
Isabella, Charles' sister.
Under French law, the crown could not
pass matrilineally.
So, Edward's claim was invalid in
France.
But, England had no such prohibition on
female succession. So, to their domestic
audiences, both kings had a valid
[music] claim to the French throne.
In 1337, Philip of Valois demanded
[music]
that all French territory serve the
French crown, including territories
whose lords were bound to the King of
England.
This ended an uneasy arrangement that
had existed since 1066, and France
launched an invasion of Gascony.
Edward responded by reasserting his
claim to the French throne and launching
an invasion of France.
Both of these claims would be maintained
by the heirs and successors of both
England and France, and so began the
Hundred Years' War.
The war had three main phases. The
first, the Edwardian phase, saw the
forces of Edward the III gain the upper
hand over the French,
culminating in the capture of the French
king at the Battle of Poitiers in 1356,
and ended with the Treaty of Brétigny in
1360, after English attempts to take
northern France floundered.
The second, Caroline phase lasted from
to 1389,
where the French, under King Charles V
the Wise, retook almost all of the
territory ceded in the Treaty of
Brétigny
before his death in 1380.
Things were going so well that a joint
French Burgundian invasion of England
was attempted in 1386.
But, poor logistics and weather
prevented it from sailing while costing
a fortune.
This setback, combined with serious
unrest in both England and France
throughout the 1380s over the high cost
of the war, meant the French were unable
to finish the job and peace was agreed
in 1389.
In 1415, [music]
the final Lancastrian phase began with
King Henry V of England spotting an
outstanding opportunity.
Burgundy had switched sides to support
England. And the French King Charles VI
had suffered from a serious mental
illness since 1392 that caused bouts of
paranoia and amnesia.
With the French lacking allies and clear
leadership, Henry won a stunning victory
at Agincourt, then took Normandy as the
Burgundians [music] took Paris.
The Treaty of Troyes in 1420 married
Henry [music] to Charles VI's daughter
Catherine and their children were
acknowledged as the future kings of
France.
Charles VII, titled the Dauphin, was
delegitimized as the heir of France, but
he continued to fight.
His fate seemed all but doomed.
Yet, within a span of just three weeks,
both Henry V and Charles VI would die of
natural causes.
This reinvigorated the cause of the
Dauphin.
Yet, the English were nonetheless eager
to finish the fight in the name of the
newly crowned infant King Henry VI.
Fresh offensives now cut into the lands
of the Dauphin.
In 1424,
at the Battle of Verneuil,
the English crushed the Franco-Scottish
field army, including the powerful Scots
Guard.
This relegated the Dauphin's alliance to
holding out [music] as best they could
in fortified towns and castles.
Yet, the English persisted in their slow
advance, and by 1428, they had laid
siege to the important city of Orléans.
If it were to fall,
the invaders would be free to thrust
deep into the heart of central France.
It was there
that Joan of Arc would emerge to change
the course of the war.
We can pass you over to our friends at
History Adventures for the maiden's
introduction from her humble origins in
the town of Domremy.
>> What do we know about her? She was an
ordinary girl living with her parents,
not a poor shepherdess as she's often
portrayed. On the contrary, she grew up
in a fairly well-off farming family with
brothers and one sister.
Their house, it still stands, sits in
the center of the village near the
church. According to her mother, the
girl could not read or write, but she
knew three prayers by heart. Joan said
that from the age of 13, she began to
hear voices. Saint Michael appeared to
her, sometimes Gabriel, along with Saint
Catherine and Saint [music] Margaret. It
was they who confused the girl, urged
her to leave home and go save her
country. At 17, she obeyed them.
To us, her claims of seeing saints may
sound strange, but at the time, people
treated it quite calmly.
There was even a notion of visionary
experience, a tendency to see mystical
visions.
In the 14th and 15th centuries, there
were famous mystics and visionaries like
[music] Saint Catherine of Siena and
Bridget of Sweden.
They described vivid, emotional visions,
scenes of heaven and the passion of
Christ, appearances of Jesus and the
Virgin Mary. So, for a medieval person,
this was nothing unusual. And later,
[music]
Joan's contemporaries argued not about
whether the visions were real, but about
who sent them, God or the devil.
The first person to believe her was her
uncle, and soon the local townspeople
joined him. Of course, the practical
knight Baudricourt did not believe her
at first.
But later, whether because she predicted
the outcome of a battle she could not
possibly have known, or because of the
rumors spreading through the town, or
maybe because of all of it together, he
finally gave her what she asked for and
sent her to Chinon. Joan spent 11 long
days on the road. Half of her route lay
under the control of the English and the
Burgundians. And still she crossed those
hostile lands with only a few escorts at
her side, and now was asking to see the
future king. Charles hesitated for a
long time about meeting her. First,
midwives examined her. A maiden meant a
virgin, and that had to be confirmed.
Then church officials questioned her.
Only after that did the dauphin receive
her. At last, the meeting she had
traveled so far for finally took place.
>> According to legend, this encounter was
yet another test passed with flying
colors [music] as the maiden was able to
pick out the dauphin hiding amidst the
attendant crowd.
History Adventures does a great job
diving into the veracity of this tale
while shedding light on the intricacies
of court politics at the time.
You can watch their full video [music]
for more details.
For the sake of our story though, Joan
had now proven herself [music]
before the highest powers of the realm.
And after yet one more test to verify
the purity of her devotion, she was
deemed ready to join the army.
To commemorate [music] this event, the
dauphin had a plate of armor
commissioned for this messenger from
God.
He also assigned her two pages, five war
horses, [music] and seven trotters.
Meanwhile, Joan herself fashioned a
personal banner whilst being apparently
guided by saints to discover an ancient
sword behind the altar of the Chapel of
St. Catherine.
Thus equipped,
>> [music]
>> the maiden was ready to fulfill her holy
mission.
As Joan set off to war, it will now be
worth revisiting the nature of the
French army she was keen to lead.
After nearly a century, it had undergone
significant change. The old banner
system was in shambles, a casualty of
the long grueling war that had torn
apart and reshaped the geopolitical
landscape of France, as well as the
broader socioeconomic trends that
followed the brutal cullings [music] of
the Black Death, which claimed some 5
million souls in France alone, the
equivalent tally of an entire British
Isles.
Because of all this, the tax base and
manpower pool available to the lords had
been significantly degraded. Training
and equipping new soldiers under such
conditions proved difficult, leading
many to simply raise fewer troops.
But, the war efforts nonetheless
continued to demand a high level of
mobilization for offensives that always
seemed to get bogged down in attritional
raids and sieges. So, they had to find
soldiers from somewhere.
Filling this gap would be an emerging
rank of middle-class soldiers [music]
who could muster the funds to train and
equip themselves.
Armies were further padded out by the
employment of small bands of
professional soldiers, often from
disbanded mercenary companies, who could
also bring to bear their own gear and
even support staff.
While this helped mitigate troop
shortages, it also led to an even more
eclectic and ad [music] hoc army
organization.
This makes it difficult to lay out the
true size of a French army of the period
as each one was its own bespoke entity.
For our purposes today, we shall do our
best to model the army which coalesced
around the banner of Joan of Arc.
This began quite small, and so now it
makes sense to start on the level of the
individual.
Here, the typical soldiers are somewhat
[music] similar to those from the start
of the Hundred Years War.
The main difference being the
aforementioned increase in the
proportion of non-noble troops,
especially among the men-at-arms.
Another major difference is the
proliferation of plate armor, made
possible by the invention of the blast
furnace in the mid-14th century.
And finally, we can make notes of the
increasing use of firearms and
artillery.
The latter proved most [music] impactful
in their ability to bring down
fortifications and with us being
gathered in ever-increasingly [music]
large siege trains.
By the end of the 15th century, [music]
all of these troops would come to form
the backbone of a new centralized
professional army.
For now though, they remained embedded
within the messy patchwork of banners
that was tasked with holding the English
at bay.
With this context [music] in mind, let
us now return to the front lines of the
war.
We find ourselves in the last week of
April in 1429
as Joan of Arc sets out from Blois for
the besieged town of Orléans.
The 17-year-old maiden has yet to prove
herself in battle and so was initially
attached to a force of around 500 men.
Hardly an army, but certainly an upgrade
from the handful of companions which had
accompanied Joan when she first set off
from home.
Yet, she was still not in charge.
Rather, this was a supply convoy under
Jean de Brosse, the Marshal of France.
Its makeup goes unreported and so we
shall assume that it largely consists of
militia troops with but a small body of
men-at-arms.
As the force marched towards the English
lines, Joan insisted upon taking the
fight to them immediately.
However, she held no military authority
and Jean de Brosse ignored her requests.
Even going so far as to lie about their
route to discourage her from further
pressing the issue.
For now, their objective was to run the
blockade of Orléans and bring the city
vital supplies, not to break the siege
entirely.
As the relief force approached Orléans,
they would have found it surrounded by
some 5,000 English troops.
Normally, slipping past such a force
would have proved difficult.
However, in this case, the English siege
works consisted of a series of
fortifications rather than a continuous
trench line.
As a result, Joan's relief force was
able to enter the less guarded southern
flank.
According to legend, this was made
possible by way of ferry boats which
were miraculously able to make the
crossing when the winds blew and the
waters rose upon the maiden's arrival.
Yet again, a sign had been made that she
was the chosen one.
Once inside, their troops joined forces
with the roughly 4,000 strong army of
Count Jean de Dunois, known as the
Bastard of Orléans,
and [music] his commoner deputy,
nicknamed La Hire, or the Hedgehog.
The defenders included an eclectic
assortment of men-at-arms, spearmen,
swordsmen, archers, [music]
crossbowmen, gunners, cannoneers, and
even rockets.
While some were professionals, at least
half of the defenders were citizens who
had taken up arms.
After 6 months of siege and recent
losses at the Battle of Herrings, morale
was at rock bottom, and the city was on
the verge of surrender.
But, fortunes were turning.
The Burgundians contingent of the
besieging army had decamped, slightly
loosening the stranglehold on Orléans.
And now, word was spreading of the
arrival of a miraculous young woman who
spoke to angels and assured the French
that she had come to bring forth a
prophesied victory that would cast the
English out once and for [music] all.
With morale on the upswing and the
prospect of more reinforcements on the
way, the French commanders now decided
to take the eastern fort of Saint Loup
to secure this vital access way to the
city.
At noon of May 4th, some 1,500
men-at-arms and militiamen charged the
position.
The 400 troops of the English garrison
responded in kind with crossbow and
handgun fire.
This took a heavy toll on the assailants
and may have threatened to collapse
their resolve.
At the same time, the western flank of
the city saw clashes as the English
began to mobilize for a counter-attack
and a French force of 600 launched their
own diversionary sortie.
Much could go wrong in this pivotal
moment.
Joan was apparently not made aware
[music]
of the initial war plans.
Yet, as soon as she heard of the
fighting, the maiden charged into the
fray of Saint Loup.
With her arms and her banners at their
side, [music]
the French were now able to steel their
morale to make the final storming of the
position.
It was a bloody affair
with the bulk of the English
slaughtered.
However, when survivors were found
hiding in the ruins of a nearby church,
Joan of Arc showed mercy, requesting
that their lives be spared.
With victory had to the east, the
western forces now retired to their
positions.
The next day, the 5th of May, was spent
honoring the peace of Ascension Day with
feasts and with rest.
Time was also spent deliberating on the
city's [music] next moves.
A war council ultimately decided to
focus on clearing out the English from
the south bank of the river.
While many in leadership wished to
approach such matters with caution, it
seems that Joan of Arc was emphatic on
pressing matters most urgently.
By now, many of the common folk were
turning to her for inspiration and the
next morning, a large number of soldiers
[music] and newly armed city militia
were rallying at her side, clamoring to
launch an assault immediately.
Some attempt was made by the senior
captains to hold them back, but when
Joan stepped into the fort in protest,
they relented.
Thousands of defenders now streamed from
the city, swarming across the river in
makeshift rafts and pontoon bridges.
Seeing this great host suddenly
approaching, the English abandoned their
outermost fort of Saint Jean de Blanc to
regroup around the more defensible
position of Les Tourelles.
The French seized their former position
and would go on to sweep through the
outermost Boulevard de Augustins before
nightfall. In these efforts, Joan would
take part in the charges.
Chroniclers state that she proved
instrumental in rallying the French when
a counter-attack nearly routed the
offensive.
But, her gallantry came at a cost when
she was injured in the foot by an iron
spike trap.
That night, she pulled back to Orléans
for recovery.
Despite many urging her to rest in
safety, Joan proved eager to join the
army and set off the next morning to
lead them in the final assault on the
fortified bridgehead of Les Tourelles.
In her wake, swarmed more militia troops
and even heavy cannons, which were
dragged out for the planned assault.
What followed would be a full day of
heavy fighting as waves of French troops
swarmed the entrenched English
fortifications, which were defended by
some 800 men and a large number of
cannons.
French guns from both sides of Les
Tourelles began the action by bombarding
[music] the defenses whilst the assault
parties moved into position.
Soon, the assailants were unleashing
volleys of arrows, bolts, and lead
rounds to cover the advance of the
assault teams.
The English responded in kind with their
own devastating fire.
Casualties quickly mounted. Joan herself
was even struck by an English arrow that
slipped through a joint in her plate
armor,
penetrating deeply between her neck
[music] and shoulder.
Nevertheless, she fought on.
A French knight would later recall her
actions as follows, quote,
"In these assaults, she was so valorous
and comported herself in such manner as
would not have been possible to any man,
however well versed in war.
And all the captains marveled at her
valor and activity and at her
endurance."
Yet, despite the pressure of the
assault, by evening it still showed no
signs of a breakthrough.
As the sun began to set, the commanders
now considered a retreat.
But, once more, Joan urged them on.
Taking a few minutes to pray, she then
returned with an inspired proclamation
that once her banner touched the
fortress battlements, it would fall.
Thus assured, the men redoubled their
efforts.
The French swarmed in from all sides
with their ladders, storming the walls
with unparalleled intensity.
Joan, too, was among them, and when her
banner hit the walls, she cried out,
"Orleans is yours. Go in!"
The assault now overran Les Tourelles,
pusing the English back to their last
redoubt.
However, in the press of their retreat,
the bridge collapsed out from under
them.
Many were killed, including the
commander Glasdale.
The remaining defenders surrendered.
The next day, the English were forced to
reckon with the situation.
Tactically, they were still in a
position to hold out against and even
strike back at the French.
However, strategically,
their position was untenable as Orléans
could now freely be resupplied from the
south and the east.
Thus, on May 8th, the English began to
decamp.
Yet, in a final save of face, they
deployed in the field offering battle.
The French emerged from Orléans to line
up before them.
Both sides stood [music] their ground
defiantly.
Finally, the English blinked first and
began their withdrawal in earnest.
After 210 days, the siege of Orléans had
finally ended.
Word of Joan's deeds [music] soon spread
far and wide.
With them came new layers of
embellishment building her up as a
legendary figure
often going so far as to reframe her
origin story.
We'll pass you back to History
Adventures for a look at what was being
said.
>> The legend around her began to take on
new layers. People spoke of her
everywhere. Here is what her
contemporary, the French knight Perceval
de Vlennvillia, wrote to the Duke of
Milan. Just listen carefully to this.
She was born on the night of the Lord's
Epiphany
when all people joyfully praised the
deeds of Christ. The whole village was
seized by an unexplained joy. And not
knowing that the maiden had been born,
they ran back and forth
asking each other what had happened.
Some hearts felt a strange delight they
had never known before. [music] And
roosters, like heralds of joyful news,
crowed for two full hours as they had
never crowed before. And they beat their
wings,
>> [music]
>> and it seemed they were foretelling some
great event.
Do you understand [music] what this kind
of description meant to a medieval
person? He claims that Joan was born on
a deeply important Christian feast day,
celebrated each year on January 6th, and
the crowing of roosters signified not
only the start of a new day, but the
[music] defeat of evil forces. In
medieval Europe, there was a belief that
at Christ's [music] birth, the roosters
crowed without pause. So, even her birth
is presented in the letter as a miracle.
>> The appeal of such stories only [music]
grew stronger as they were accompanied
with fresh tidings of victory from the
battlefield.
But, Joan was only getting started.
Join us next time as we follow the
ever-growing size of Joan's reputation
and her [music] army as it sets off to
turn the tide of the Hundred Years' War.
The Loire Valley was still in the grip
of the English, and beyond it lay the
grander [music] prizes of Reims and
Paris.
Only one touched by God could lead the
way.
Thank you once again for joining us in
this episode, and be sure to check out
our friends over at History Adventures
[music]
for more amazing documentaries.
A big thanks to [music] our fans on
Patreon and YouTube memberships for
supporting the channel, and to the
researchers, writers, and artists for
making this episode possible. We
couldn't have done it without this team
and this community.
If you liked this episode, be sure to
like and subscribe for more content, and
check out these other related videos.
See you in the The next one.